OpenAI has introduced a new tool named GPTBot,
marking a significant milestone in the effort
to develop artificial intelligence.
GPTBot is an automated web data collector
with the ability to navigate the entire internet
and gather text from web pages.
The vast amount of textual data that GPTBot
can accumulate will provide a valuable resource
for training OpenAI's upcoming language models.
Specifically, GPTBot is designed to support
GPT-5, the next iteration of the renowned
language model after GPT-4.
With GPT-5, OpenAI aims to achieve a breakthrough
in the development of Artificial General Intelligence
(AGI).
Upon success, GPT-5 will be the first AI model
capable of thinking, reasoning, and problem-solving
at a human-like level.
This will unlock new applications and possibilities
for AI that we have never seen before.
In reality, the reason behind ChatGPT's ability
to generate such great content lies in the
massive amount of text data collected from
the internet, all thanks to GPTBot.
It's like an enormous information library
that the models use to understand and respond
to your requests.
And if you're curious about how GPTBot selects
which websites to explore and which ones to
avoid, GPTBot follows specific rules and principles
to ensure the collected data is of high quality
and respects both privacy rights and the rights
of individuals.
To illustrate, GPTBot exclusively explores
websites that anyone can access without needing
to go through paywalls or log in with usernames
and passwords.
It deliberately avoids collecting data from
websites containing Personally Identifiable
Information (PII), such as names, addresses,
phone numbers, or email addresses of individuals.
Moreover, it filters out content that violates
OpenAI's policies, such as content containing
provocative, violent, or explicit language.
But what if you're a website owner and you
don't want GPTBot to gather data from your
website?
You have the option to do that.
You can insert a specific line into your website's
robots.txt file to instruct the information-gathering
process to stay away from your website.
This requires GPTBot not to crawl any pages
on your website.
Now, GPT-5 is the next major language model
expected from OpenAI, following the previous
releases of GPT-3.5 and GPT-4.
Although there's still very little information
about it, there are some clues indicating
that OpenAI is working on it and has plans
to release it soon.
For instance, OpenAI filed a trademark application
for "GPT-5" with the United States Patent
and Trademark Office (USPTO) in July 2023.
This application covers various types of software
related to language models and AI.
The application is currently pending examination
by the USPTO.
But what can we expect from GPT-5 in terms
of capabilities and features?
Well, based on previous versions of the GPT
model, we can assume GPT-5 will be a major
upgrade over GPT-4 in size, accuracy, and
flexibility.
For example:
In terms of size, GPT-4 comprised 175 billion
parameters.
This was already hugely significant when comparing
it to most other existing language models.
Now, GPT-5 is predicted to have an even larger
number of parameters, potentially in the trillions.
What does this mean for us?
Basically, GPT-5 will be able to store more
information and have a larger memory capacity
than any human, making it an extremely powerful
tool.
When it comes to accuracy, GPT-4 demonstrated
superior performance on various natural language
processing (NLP) tasks and benchmarks.
These include areas like natural language
understanding (NLU), natural language generation
(NLG), question answering (QA), etc.
However, GPT-5 is expected to surpass these
achievements even further.
It may reach new heights in accuracy and fluency,
generating text and speech that is more human-like
in communication.
Flexibility is another area where GPT-5 will
excel.
GPT-4 was already able to handle various types
of inputs and outputs, such as text, speech,
images, and code.
However, GPT-5 may take this even further,
expanding its multimodal capabilities.
It may also be able to sync with third-party
platforms and tools, such as social media
platforms, search engines, and productivity
tools (e.g. Microsoft Office).
These improvements will make GPT-5 more adaptable
and useful across different industries and
applications.
Now, one question many may wonder is when
will GPT-5 be released?
This is really a tricky question to answer,
mainly because OpenAI has not provided any
official timelines or announcements related
to the GPT-5 launch.
But we can try to make some educated guesses
based on release patterns of previous iterations.
GPT-3.5 was introduced in November 2022, followed
by GPT-4 in March 2023, making those two iterations
roughly 4 months apart.
If this trend continues, we could potentially
see GPT-5 by late this year.
However, it's important to recognize this
is just speculation with some basis.
The ever-changing AI ecosystem can cause unexpected
delays or setbacks that could alter GPT-5's
release date.
One of the most intriguing and controversial
questions surrounding GPT-5 is whether or
not it will reach the level of artificial
general intelligence or AGI.
To understand this, we first need to know
what AGI is.
It is a theoretical concept of an AI that
could learn and understand anything a human
can.
This should not be confused with what we have
today, called narrow AI, where AI can only
perform certain specific tasks or functions.
AGI represents a higher level of AI, one that
is not limited to particular capabilities.
There have been some initial reports and rumors
that GPT-5 could achieve AGI by late 2023.
People are making this claim because they
believe GPT-5 will generate text and speech
so realistic it will be indistinguishable
from human communication.
They also think it will be able to answer
any question or prompt a human can handle.
But most experts and researchers view this
idea as far-fetched and too early to predict.
They emphasize we could still be many years
away from AGI and GPT-5 will face various
obstacles and limitations, especially around
generalization, reasoning, common sense, and
ethical considerations.
So what would happen if GPT-5 does achieve
AGI?
This is a complex topic, but let's try to
summarize it.
On the positive side, GPT-5 could boost productivity
and creativity by accelerating AI-assisted
processes, freeing humans from repetitive
tasks.
This could lead to breakthroughs in areas
like education, entertainment, and media by
providing relevant, engaging content and services.
On the other hand, there could be significant
risks.
GPT-5 could harm human society and principles
by spreading misinformation, propaganda, or
engaging in manipulation.
Ethical concerns and ethically-challenging
situations could also arise, challenging human
dignity, identity, and freedom.
Now, I'd like to know your perspective on
GPT-5 and its potential for achieving AGI.
Is this something you believe could happen
or do you find it unlikely?
Is it a breakthrough or a murky issue?
Share your thoughts in the comments below.
If you found this video interesting, please
like and share it with your friends.
Be sure to subscribe to my channel to learn
more about AI advancements.
Thank you for watching and I'll see you in
the next video.